<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A charge against the Jews, and the Christian world, for not coming to Christ, who would have freely given them eternall life. Delivered in a sermon, before the Right Honorable the House of Peers, in the Abbey Church at Westminster, on May 26. 1647. being the day of their publick fast. / By Thomas Valentine, one of the Assembly of Divines, and Minister of Chalfont in the County of Bucks.</title>
            <author>Valentine, Thomas, 1585 or 6-1665?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1647</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 79 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A95857</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing V24</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E389_6</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R201520</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99862020</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99862020</idno>
            <idno type="VID">114168</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A95857)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 114168)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 62:E389[6])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A charge against the Jews, and the Christian world, for not coming to Christ, who would have freely given them eternall life. Delivered in a sermon, before the Right Honorable the House of Peers, in the Abbey Church at Westminster, on May 26. 1647. being the day of their publick fast. / By Thomas Valentine, one of the Assembly of Divines, and Minister of Chalfont in the County of Bucks.</title>
                  <author>Valentine, Thomas, 1585 or 6-1665?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 30 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by M.S. for John Rothwell at the Sun and Fountain in Pauls Church-yard.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London: :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1647.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  John V, 40 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Fast-day sermons --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:114168:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:114168:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A CHARGE AGAINST THE <hi>JEWS,</hi> and the Chriſtian WORLD, for not coming to CHRIST, who would have freely given them Eternall Life.</p>
            <p>DELIVERED IN A <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>RMON, before the Right <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>norable the Houſe of PEERS,</p>
            <p>In the Abbey Church at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> on <hi>May</hi> 26. 1647. Being the Day of their Publick <hi>Faſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> THOMAS VALENTINE, one of the Aſſembly of <hi>Divines,</hi> and Miniſter of <hi>Chalfont</hi> in the County of <hi>Bucks.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Nullum magis peſtiferum venenum, quam ſocordia illa quam in nobis generat aut terrenae faelicitatis, aut justitiae propriae falſa &amp; fallax opinio. <bibl>
                  <hi>Calv.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>M S.</hi> for <hi>John Rothwell</hi> at the <hi>Sun</hi> and <hi>Fountain</hi> in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard. 1647.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:114168:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:114168:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE Houſe of LORDS Aſſembled in <hi>PARLIAMENT.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honorable:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen I was called to Preach before Your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips, there was not in our view either Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, or evill occurrent; we thought we had Peace in our hands, and that all was well: but ſince that time our Diſtractions did on the ſudden grow great and dangerous. We ſtand in need of the goodneſſe of God to come in ſeaſonablie to our Reſcue, and it will require the wiſdom and diligence of your Lordſhips, and all others to compoſe theſe Differences, that they riſe no higher, nor end ill. We may look upon them with ſadneſſe, and ſorrow of heart, and fear leſt Gods anger is not turned away from us; We have need to ſecond our Faſts with doing all things an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable, leſt if we contradict our prayers by looſeneſſe of life, God give us an Anſwer contrary to our expectation. It is high time to lay down our provocations againſt God, and bitterneſſe of ſpirit one againſt another; our contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons have been ſo hot, that we have departed one from ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; let us take heed of endeavouring to root out one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and to avoid rancor and virulencie of ſpirit. Next to the directions and examples of Scripture, I could wiſh we had caſt our eyes upon ſome part of the <hi>Carthaginian</hi> Story, and ſee what was the iſſue of the diſſention between
<pb facs="tcp:114168:3"/> them and the <hi>Romanes;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <p>
                     <hi>Amilchar uſed to ſay his</hi> 4. <hi>ſons that he did</hi> Alere quatuor catulos leoni nos in perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciem &amp; exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minium Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mani imperii, <hi>but it proved contrary.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Hannibal pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mogenitus ejus aetatis c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>to annorum acce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens ad ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficium juravit quod quum primum eſſet adultae aeta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis foret a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trociſſimus hoſtis Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norum qui dum excitaſſet pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veres cum pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dibus, ait, tunc erit pax inter Carthaginen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes &amp; Romanos quando altera iſtarum civita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum erit in pulverem re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dacta.</p>
               </note> the <hi>Carthaginians</hi> could never be perſwaded to have any peace with <hi>Rome,</hi> though ſome of their Nobility much endeavoured it. <hi>Amilcar</hi> when he went out in an expedition did offer ſacrifice, and <hi>Hanni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ball</hi> the great, his eldeſt Son, being preſent at the ſolemnity with his Father when he was but young, had received in ſuch principles of War and oppoſition, that he vowed to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond his Fathers deſignes, and ſaid there ſhould be peace be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ween <hi>Carthage</hi> and <hi>Rome,</hi> when one of thoſe Cities ſhould be as that duſt which he then ſpurned up with his foot; it proved fatall to that ſide which was reſolved to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the other. For though <hi>Hanniball</hi> was the braveſt Commander that ever <hi>Carthage</hi> bred, and had many Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctories, and great ſucceſſe, for ſixteen yeers together, yet ſhortly after <hi>Carthage</hi> was fiered by the <hi>Romanes,</hi> and was upon a flame <hi>17.</hi> dayes together, and conſumed into duſt and aſhes. Let there be no ſuch ſpirit in the parties that oppoſe one another; let all ſides-taking be layed aſide and the names that intimate diviſion be extinguiſhed: let there be a calm temper, and a wiſe Accommodation, leſt both ſides be pulled down one after the other: that Your Lordſhips may be the happie Inſtruments to prevent ſo great an evill, and effect ſo great a good, is the Prayer of him who reſts,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips to be commanded in the ſervice of the Goſpel, THO: VALENTINE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:114168:3"/>
            <head>A SERMON PREACHED Before the Right Honorable Houſe of LORDS.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>JOH. 5.40.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>And ye will not come to me that ye might have life.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">J</seg>Eſus Chriſt was ſo amiable in his life, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable in all his ſpeeches, ſo holy in his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation, ſo wiſe in all his anſwers to his ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>villing adverſaries, ſo meek in teaching the ignorant, ſo ready to cure diſeaſes and infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities: that one would have thought all men would be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken with him, and have come unto him. But nothing leſſe, they that came to him were ready to leave him, and others would not come at all; which makes him take it unkindly (for ſo theſe words are to be underſtood) you <hi>will not come to me.</hi> Deceivers ſpeak to you, Satan and the world invite you, and you go to them; I call and perſwade you, but you will not come to me: they will bring you to miſerie and death; I would give you happineſſe and life, but you will not come to me.</p>
            <p>The ill carriage of men towards Chriſt, was anſwered ſometimes with indignation.</p>
            <p n="1">1. As that meſſage to <hi>Herod, Go tell that Fox, Behold,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 13.32.</note> 
               <hi>I caſt out devils, and will heal to day and to morrow, and the third day I ſhall be perfected.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Sometimes with deteſtation of their ſinfulneſſe,<note place="margin">Man. 23.27.</note> 
               <hi>Wo to you Scribes Phariſees, hypocrites; you are like painted tombes, and whited ſepulchers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Sometimes with compaſſion to them, and grief to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf;
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:114168:4"/> as that in <hi>John, Will you alſo go away?</hi> And here in the text,<note place="margin">Ioh 6.67.</note> 
               <hi>You will not come to me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This whole Chapter is a defence of Chriſt againſt the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>villing Jews, which found fault with his cure done upon the impotent man that lay by the Pool of Betheſda, and had an infirmitie 38. yeers, and was ſo impotent that others pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented him, and got into the pool upon the moving of the waters; and thus he continued till Chriſt came up to the Feaſt at Jeruſalem: and finding him there, takes pity upon him, and cures him, as you ſee in <hi>ver.</hi> 5, 6, 7, 8. And it being the Sabbath day they find fault with the fact, and alſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he took up his bed; and queſtion with the man, inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring who it was that did it, from <hi>ver.</hi> 10. to 13. But he not knowing who it was, could make no anſwer, till afterwards Chriſt finding him in the Temple makes himſelf known unto him, and gives him an admonition to <hi>ſin no more, leſt a worſe thing befall him:</hi> v. 14. Then the man told the Jews it was Jeſus that made him whole, which moved them to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute him, <hi>v.</hi> 15, 16. Then begins our Saviour to make his defence, from <hi>v.</hi> 17. to the end; wherein he affirms his Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and his equality with his Father, which made the Jews to be more enraged againſt him, <hi>v.</hi> 18. But he goes on to ſhew that what he did, his Father did: <hi>My Father worketh hitherto, and I work:</hi> I can do nothing of my ſelf. The Father hath life in himſelf, and ſo hath the Son; and the Father hath committed all judgement to the Son. And if you begin at <hi>v.</hi> 31. and read on, you may find that he layes aſide his own teſtimony, and inſiſts on five more, every one of which were ſufficient to convince them that he was the Son of God, and that they ought to come unto him. 1. The teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of his Father, <hi>ver.</hi> 32.37. There is another which beareth witneſſe of me, and who that is, <hi>v.</hi> 37. ſhews, <hi>The Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther himſelf which hath ſent me, beareth witneſſe of me.</hi> 2. The te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonie of <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt, <hi>v.</hi> 33. <hi>And ye rejoyced in him, and he bare witneſſe of me.</hi> 3. His works and miracles, <hi>v.</hi> 36. <hi>The works that the Father hath given me to finiſh, the ſame works that I do, bear witneſſe of me, that the Father hath ſent me.</hi> 4. The Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, <hi>v.</hi> 39. <hi>Search the Scriptures, for in them ye think to have eternall life, and they are they which teſtifie of me.</hi> 5. The laſt teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:114168:4"/> alledged is that of <hi>Moſes, v.</hi> 46. <hi>Had ye beleeved Moſes you would have beleeved me, for he wrote of me.</hi> The ſumme of all is, I have the teſtimony of my Father, and of <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt, and of my works and miracles, and of the Scriptures, an of <hi>Moſes:</hi> but none of theſe will convince you, you will not come to me, and therefore your ſin is great.</p>
            <p>In the text you have, 1. the illation or inference <hi>[and]</hi> which according to the ſence was formerly tranſlated; but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> being often put for <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as <hi>Beza</hi> obſerves.</p>
            <p n="2">2. There is the ſin reproved in the Jews, <hi>You will not come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The perſon to whom they ſhould have come, but did not, <hi>[me.]</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. The end which they might have attained, but did not, <hi>That ye might have life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>[And]</hi> muſt not be underſtood as a copulative,<note place="margin">The ſence of the text.</note> but diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretive, therefore in the ſence it is but <hi>You will not come to me.</hi> It ſhews the wicked and obſtinate nature of the Jews, though they had ſo many clear teſtimonies of Chriſt, yet they would not imbrace him, you Jews will not come, therefore your ſin is the greater; the Gentiles have no knowledge of me, it cannot be expected, that they ſhould come: but you Jews that have knowledge of the propheſies, and promiſes, and of the Law, that are a light to them that ſit in darknes, teachers of the unlearned, inſtructers of them that lack diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion, you offend the more in not coming to me.</p>
            <p>You <hi>[will not]</hi> our Saviour ſaith not, you cannot, but,<note place="margin">
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</p>
                  <p>Non dicit non venitis ſed non vultis venire &amp; cum cos nolle dicit ignoran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae &amp; caeritatis cauſam pravi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tati &amp; contu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matiae aſſignat. Muſcul.</p>
               </note> 
               <hi>you will not come:</hi> the wilfulneſſe of their ſpirits is ſet out, there are three diſtinct degrees.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Men do not come. 2. They cannot come. 3. They will not come to Chriſt. The firſt is their careleſneſſe and negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, the ſecond is their weakneſſe and impotencie, the third is their wilfulneſſe and great wickedneſſe; and the laſt is the reſult of all, men do not come to Chriſt, becauſe they will not come: and they cannot come, becauſe they will not: their wills muſt be ſubdued, and the rebellion thereof muſt be removed, elſe they neither can nor will come to Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>[Not come]</hi> You will not beleeve in me; that's the ſin, but with an aggravation, you will not ſo much as come unto
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:114168:5"/> me; they would not vouchſafe him any reſpect, they would not frequent his company, nor willingly be in his preſence.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>[That ye might have life.]</hi> We muſt not imagine that they were out of love with life, for that's deſirable by all, and it cannot fall upon the reaſonable creature ſimplie to deſire not to live; ſo as the reaſon of their not coming was not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he did not offer them that which was pleaſing and amiable, but they were ſo far out of love with him, and ſo much prejudiced againſt him, that they would not come unto him, though they might have life.</p>
            <p>Or elſe they would not come unto him for a right end, that they might have life. Ye will come to me for the loafes that I might feed you, and for by-ends; if I came like a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quering <hi>Alexander,</hi> with an Army to deliver you from the power of the Romane Monarchie, and to repair the glory of your decayed kingdom, you would come unto me: but to have life, and to obtain ſalvation, ye will not come un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me.</p>
            <p>The words briefly thus explained afford two ſeverall Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The great condemning ſin, which will be charged upon the Jews, and the Chriſtian world, is that they would not come to Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="2">2 That Jeſus Chriſt will freely give eternall life, to them that come unto him.</p>
            <p>To come to Chriſt is not any locall motion, or change of place; for go all the world over and you cannot find him; he is aſcended into heaven, and whither he, is gone ye can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not come. When this was ſpoken it was ſpiritually to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, if a man had been in Chriſts preſence, and ſtayed long with him, nay if he had taken him into his arms, if he had not received him into his heart by faith, it would not have availed. Therefore underſtand it thus.</p>
            <p n="1">1: To come to Chriſt, is to have recourſe unto him, and acknowledge him worthy of all reſpect: all that came unto him d d not beleeve in him; but theſe will vouchſafe him no honour, they diſdain him, and caſt ſcorn and contempt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him in not coming to him.</p>
            <p>Foure things move us to come to an other, the command
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:114168:5"/> of one in authority, the <hi>Centurion ſaith to me, Go, and he goeth:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 8 9.</note> 
               <hi>to another, Come, and he cometh;</hi> Chriſt was a King,<note place="margin">Pſal. 2.6.</note> for God ſet his King upon his holy hill of <hi>Sion,</hi> and all power in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and earth was given him. Kings have power,<note place="margin">Honorant ut Regem, ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant ut Deum, vident enim hominem, &amp; agnoſcunt Deum.</note> but not all power, they have a conditionall, temporarie, externall po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, derived from Chriſt. But he hath an abſolute, eternall, primative power, which all men ſhould acknowledge and ſtoope unto; the wiſe men (the firſt fruites of the <hi>Gentiles</hi>) they came unto Chriſt, and they did acknowledge him, and ask boldly, <hi>Where is he that is born King of the Jews?</hi> this might juſtly ſhame the <hi>Jewes,</hi> they came to him while he was a young Infant, and found him in a mean condition,<note place="margin">
                  <p>Adorant magi, &amp; offerunt munera adhuc lact<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nti ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tris ubera.</p>
                  <p>Bern.</p>
                  <p>Parvulum non honoraſſent nec adoraſſent ſi parvulum tantummodo credidiſſent.</p>
               </note> ſucking of his mothers breaſts, they came from farre and preſent him with gold franckincenſe, and mirrhe; gold be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he was a King, frankincenſe as he was God, for that was uſed in the offerings, and mirrhe as he was man, here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they honoured him much, and were readie to tender their homage to him: but the <hi>Iewes</hi> would not come unto him.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Neceſſity might have made them come unto him, for he was the onely remedie that God appointed for their at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonement, the onely ſacrifice that was propitiatorie, they might have known that all the ſacrifices under the Law d d looke at him, they had their life from him, and alſo their death from him; for when he offered up himſelfe,<note place="margin">
                  <p>Magna pars mundi, accede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re ideo negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>git quia neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitatis ſuae ſenſu non tangitur.</p>
                  <p>Chriſtum non curant hipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>critae, quia ebrii juſtitit propria grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am ejus non ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iunt.</p>
                  <p>ex innumera pereuntium turba pauci ſe perire ſentium Calv.</p>
               </note> they were to ſurceaſe; their Prieſts, eſpecially their high Prieſts did ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pifie him, and all the legall ſervices and ſacrifices without him were nothing. Had they known their neceſſity they would have come unto him, pain and apprehenſion of the danger of a diſeaſe, will quickly convince the ſicke, that there is a neceſſity of having recourſe to a Phiſitian, but theſe <hi>Iewes</hi> were ignorant, and inſenſible of their miſerie, and though Chriſt was the onely Phiſitian, yet they will not come unto him.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Love makes us to come to friends, and often viſit them; and had they known the good things that Chriſt brought to man, and the goodneſſe that was in himſelf, they would have been taken with him, he honoured our nature, and brought ſalvation to our ſoules, he honoured man in that
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:114168:6"/> he was made man, hee honoured the <hi>Iewes</hi> in that he was of the ſeed of <hi>Abraham;</hi> he is our great benefactor, he brings us into favour with God, who were children of wrath, he repaires loſt man with an augmentation of glory; he ſets us into a right of an heavenly Paradiſe that loſt an earthly. one in <hi>Adam,</hi> he (like <hi>Jonathan</hi> to <hi>David,</hi> puts his own robe of righteouſneſſe upon us, which is a more glorious cover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing then Angels have: and had the <hi>Iewes</hi> known theſe things they would have given him more reſpect, and as he is good to man, ſo he is moſt ſweet and gracious in himſelf, obſerve his cariage (when you read the Hiſtory of his life and death in the Goſpel,) what it was to all (ſave to thoſe egregious hypocrites) the Phariſees and you will finde in him the ſweeteſt temper, the ſtrangeſt meekneſſe, the richeſt mercie, the greateſt excellency every way. If you look upon the beauty of his graces,<note place="margin">Inter iras pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cida inter mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micitias bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fica.</note> his holineſſe and wiſdom, &amp;c. You may wonder that he was no more eſteemed among men, but the <hi>Iewes</hi> not knowing his worth, nor being well affected to him will not come at him.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Eminency in Chriſt might have drawn them to him; <hi>Solomons</hi> wiſdom drew many to him, the Queen of <hi>Shebah</hi> came from farr to hear him,<note place="margin">Mat. 12.42. Ezek. 33.31.</note> and <hi>Ezekiels</hi> skilfull and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant propheſying made the people come and ſit before him; but the wiſdome and skill of Chriſt much prefer him above them. <hi>Moſes</hi> was eminent among the <hi>Iewes,</hi> ſo were the Prophets; but Chriſt much more then they, for he was the Prince of Prophets, he was the King of glory, and they his Ambaſſadors, he the Angel of the Co<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nant; he was not onely aboue Saints, and Prophets, and Apoſtles, and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, as a King above his ſubjects, but ſo above them that they muſt adore and worſhip him, what ever light came to the mindes of holy men in viſions and raptures it came from Chriſt, it was but a beame from this Sun, and the ſame argument that mooved them to honour <hi>Moſes,</hi> and credit the writings of the Old <hi>Teſtament,</hi> might have convinced them to have regarded Chriſt; but we will ſtay no longer with the unbeleiving <hi>Iew,</hi> to diſcourſe of his neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect of Chriſt, we will further explain the dutie of coming to Chriſt, and open the nature of the contrarie ſin, as it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernes
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:114168:6"/> all that live in the Chriſtian world.</p>
            <p n="2">2. To come to Chriſt preſuppoſeth a man to receive po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer from him, inabling him to come unto him,<note place="margin">Mat. 14 28.</note> it being a ſpirituall action, muſt have a ſupernaturall power, we may ſee it plainly in that command given to <hi>Peter</hi> upon his own motion, if it be thou, ſaith he to Chriſt, <hi>bid me come unto thee on the water;</hi> if Chriſt had not given out a power aſwell as a command to <hi>Peter,</hi> he had ſunk when he ſet his foot up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſea, and if another had adventured (not having the like power) he could not have come, he would have miſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried by the way; The great command of the Goſpel is gone out from Chriſt into the world and it is come unto me,<note place="margin">Mat. 11.28.</note> and the greateſt part comes not; the reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is they have not power given them to come, we muſt have virtue from Chriſt to come, as well as to be healed when we come: The dark minds of men muſt be enlightned to know Chriſt, and their rebellious wils muſt be conquered and maſtered, or elſe they wil not come unto him; for all Goſpel truths are more then thoſe of the Law, above mans underſtanding, and contrarie to his will, and if we receive them it is given us from above, <hi>No man can come to me,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>except the Father draw him;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh 6.44.</note> there is a violence offered to the corruption of the will,<note place="margin">Pſal. 65.4.</note> but none to the will it ſelf, and the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> hath the like expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, <hi>Bleſſed is the man whom thou chooſeſt and cauſeſt to come unto thee;</hi> Chriſt doth invite us, and inables us to come, and the honour of both belongs to him.</p>
            <p n="3">3. To come to Chriſt is not onely to have recourſe to him, and judge him worthy of all reſpects and to receive power from him, to inable us to come, but to go on and not ſtay till we receive ſome ſaving benefits from him. Some ſtay in the beginnings, or in preparations, and ſit down too ſoon, and looſe the benefit of their former labour, but wee muſt come on and not ſit down till we get to the jorneyes end: To come to Chriſt, is either the the firſt motion of a new convert, or elſe it is a continuall recourſe to Chriſt for increaſe of all ſaving graces, it will not be accepted to go once, or twice, and then to ſtay as the <hi>Jewes</hi> did,<note place="margin">Ier. 2.31.</note> we are Lords we will come no more unto thee, this were abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble pride and contempt, let us a litle conſider this action
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:114168:7"/> of coming to Chriſt, and in the beginning; at firſt it is ſad and uncomfortable, in the end joyfull and glorious.</p>
            <p>At firſt when we come we labour &amp; are heavie laden, the ſinner in his ſinfull courſe hath a labour, &amp; it will wearie him,<note place="margin">Mat, 11.28.</note> the penitent ſinner in his converſion hath a labour, and the combatant in his fight againſt ſin hath a labour, &amp; there is no ſuch toil as this is, no burthen ſo heavie as that of ſin; it cauſeth an univerſall pain, it is upon the conſcience indeed, but extends to the whole man, and makes him wearie of himſelf;<note place="margin">Ier. 7.12.</note> for it hath in it the vengeance of an angrie God, the torments of a flaming hell, the power of a juſt Law, and the greateſt ſinners that are moſt ſenſible of their miſerie wil come moſt humblie, and in much poverty of ſpirit; no crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſo wilde as a ſinner in his jollitie, who is as the wilde Aſſe in the wilderneſſe that runs up and down at pleaſure, none ſo tame as the penitent ſinner that is taken in his moneth, God hath humbled him, and taken down the pride of his ſpirit, he ſtood in his way as the Angel in <hi>Balaams;</hi> he threatned him he had his bowe in his hand and his ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row on the ſtring,<note place="margin">Pſal. 7.12.</note> and the ſinner not giving back, he ſhot at him and wounded him, and left the arrow ſticking in his heart:<note place="margin">Pſal. 38.2.</note> and now this wounded man, he mourns inwardly, and makes his moane to God, <hi>Thine arrowes ſtick faſt in me,</hi> is willing to come to Chriſt to be healed, and to have the arrow pluckt out, and the wound cured.</p>
            <p>Neceſſitie at firſt brings us unto Chriſt, afterward we ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend goodneſſe, and his divine perfections, and we come in love to him, we cannot ſtay away; a poore man at the doore that hath ſcarce a ragge to cover his nakedneſſe, not a peece of bread to ſatisfie nature, he comes to aske for the Maſter, not to be acquainted with him, that were boldneſſe, but to be releived in his neceſſities: ſo Chriſt is ſought unto as a Saviour, to take away our guilt, to give a pardon, to ſupply our wants, and when we are ſenſible of our miſerie, we are eaſily induced to come to Chriſt.</p>
            <p>But when we are juſtified, and accepted, and find the ſweetneſſe of fellowſhip and communion with Chriſt, then we are delighted in him; and if there were no neceſſity com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelling us, if no weakneſſe in our faith, no want in our ſouls,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:114168:7"/> yet we ſhould deſire to come to him; they that have ſeen God in any ordinance, are reſtleſſe till they ſee him again.<note place="margin">Pſal. 63.2.</note> 
               <hi>David</hi> could bear well enough his baniſhment from the Court, yet he much deſired to come to the place of Gods publick worſhip, that he might ſee his power and glory, as formerly he had ſeen them in the ſanctuary.</p>
            <p n="4">4. To come to Chriſt, is to beleeve in him; and when he complains of the Jews not coming, he chargeth them with unbelief. He that comes to God muſt beleeve that he is,<note place="margin">Credere eſt actus intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectus aſſerti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entis veritati divinae ex im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perio volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis motae à Deo per gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam. Aqui.</note> and that he is a rewarder of them that ſeek him: The Jews be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeved no ſuch thing of Chriſt, they did not think him to be God, nor that he would reward them that come to him: they gave no aſſent to what he ſpake; they did not credit him. Faith hath a double act, one more common and gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, and that is to give a firm aſſent to all Divine truth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed in the Scripture; Faith gives God the honour of his truth, as love and hope do give him the honour of his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and bountie; And truth is equally ſpread over all the Scriptures, I beleeve as verily that <hi>Iſaac</hi> was the ſon of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham,</hi> as that Chriſt is the Son of God; becauſe Scripture affirms both, and one thing cannot be more or leſſe true then another; one is more uſefull then another,<note place="margin">Fides ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guum non ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet, ſi habet, non eſt fides.</note> and condu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth more to my good, and in this generall act of faith I am to conſider of one more then another, but both are equally true, but there ſhould be, nay there is no doubtihg, though ſome men have doubted, whether this or that part of the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble were Scripture, yet a beleever muſt not doubt whether Scripture be true, that were to doubt whether God be true.</p>
            <p>The truth which faith beleeves comes by divine revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; if I can prove by reaſon that all things that are,<note place="margin">Haereticus du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitens de uno articulo fidei opinionem ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet de reliquis. Biel. Gen. 1.</note> were made by him that hath an abſolute being, and is the firſt cauſe of all, I do not beleeve it, becauſe I can prove it, but becauſe Scripture ſaith it; for <hi>in the beginning God created the heavens and the earth.</hi> The Scriptures of the Old Teſtament held out clearly the Meſſiah, and by thoſe propheſies and promiſes (wherin the Jews were very well verſt) they might know that he was the Chriſt, and yet they did beleeve nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thoſe Scriptures, nor any thing himſelf ſpake or did
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:114168:8"/> And then no wonder if they fail in the ſecond act of faith, which is to relye and reſt with confidence on Chriſt the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour;<note place="margin">Mar. 15.31.</note> they were ſo far from this that they upbraid him at his death, ſaying, <hi>He could not ſave himſelf,</hi> and therefore it was in vain to expect ſalvation from him.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Notitia aſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus &amp; fiducia</hi> are made parts of Faith: but two of them being in the underſtanding, the 3 in the Will, it may be doubted how one ſuch grace can be in two faculties. Schoolmen generally to ſalve this doubt, make gne faculty ſubordinate to the other, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Faith is <hi>Actus impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratus a volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate, elicitus ab intellectu.</hi> It is in the will <hi>ut in primo motivo, in in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellectu ut in proximo ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecto.</hi> But the doubt is, when they ſay it is <hi>ex impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rio voluntatis,</hi> they ſeem to give the precedencie to the will, to ſhun ſuch diſputes we may rather call them acts in the beleever, then parts of Faith.</note> But we have in theſe dayes all the means neceſſarie to work in us all the particulars required to a ſaving faith, we have knowledge of him, we queſtion not his Divinity, we beleeve he came with a commiſſion from heaven, we give a full and firm aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to whatſoever he ſpake, as being undoubtedly true; we would caſt our ſelves with confidence into his arms that is able to ſave us, we beleeve that God is reconciliable, that ſin is pardonable; and this we do upon the hearing of the glad tydings of the Goſpel, and afterward we grow up into a greater confidence and aſſurance of the pardon of our ſins purchaſed by his blood.</p>
            <p>But thoſe that do not beleeve ſhall have this great ſin charged upon them, and that we may clear Gods juſtice in puniſhing men that live in the Chriſtian world for their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidelity, it will be needfull to inquire where the power of beleeving lyes; for if they cannot beleeve, how is God juſt to require that of them which they have not power to do?</p>
            <p>I anſwer. <hi>Adam</hi> in his innocencie had a kinde of legall faith, whereby he was to depend upon God for the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of his promiſe; for God promiſed him life as a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of his obedience, and he was to look for it: Now what ever he had, being a publick perſon, we may be ſaid to have it, and muſt be accountable for it ſo as in him we had power to beleeve, and therefore may be puniſhed for unbelief. And this Anſwer is given by many Reverend Divines, and let it go as far as it may to the removing of the Objection.</p>
            <p>But the queſtion is, whether <hi>Adam</hi> had power to beleeve in Chriſt crucified. He did beleeve in God, and his faith was joyned with his obedience; for he obeying the voice of God was to beleeve that God would make good his promiſe to him, but his power was to the things of the Law written, in
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:114168:8"/> his heart, it was within that compaſſe and latitude, but not in the way of the Goſpel which ſuppoſeth man to be fallen, and quite over-turned; and how faith in Chriſt, which is the condition of the Covenant of grace, ſhould be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded in the Law given to <hi>Adam</hi> in his innocencie, I do not underſtand. And though he did beleeve in God, yet he might not have power to beleeve in Chriſt dying for ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners. But ſuppoſe God had revealed to <hi>Adam</hi> (while he ſtood) the event of things, and imagine he had ſaid to him, <hi>Adam,</hi> I have made thee wiſe and righteous, I have enſtamp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed mine Image upon thee, I have given thee a juſt Law, and power to keep it, and for thy reward I will give thee life; I have put thee into a pleaſant Paradiſe, where thou haſt all things for neceſſity and delight; but thou wilt diſobey my voice, and looſe thy ſelf, and forfeit all that I have given thee; yet neither thou, nor all thy poſterity ſhall periſh, I will ſend my Son into the world, to take mans nature, and dye for ſin; and life and happineſſe ſhall come by faith in him.</p>
            <p>The queſtion is, whether <hi>Adam</hi> could have beleeved up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſuch a Revelation?</p>
            <p>I anſwer: That he could and would have credited God, and beleeved the truth of this relation made unto him by his Creator: but to beleeve in Chriſt, and caſt himſelf upon a Saviour, muſt preſuppoſe him to be caſt away, and loſt.</p>
            <p>But could not <hi>Adam</hi> have promiſed to beleeve in Chriſt upon the former Revelation?</p>
            <p>I anſwer: If he had, it had not been available: for it is all one, as if a rich man worth many thouſand pounds ſhould promiſe, and give his Bond to pay me an 100 li. when he is broken, and not worth a groat.</p>
            <p>But it is very true, that men have more power, then they put out for faith and obedience, and it is as true, that infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity is in their power, and they willingly remain in un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belief. The Anſwer that men return to the invitations of Chriſt are the ſame which the Jews made unto him, <hi>How often would I have gathered thee together, as the hen her chickens,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 23.</note> 
               <hi>and ye would not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:114168:9"/>1. Further, to clear the point in hand, we may ſafely af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm, that all men in <hi>Adam</hi> ſtand guiltie of diſobedience, and God may juſtly puniſh them for that ſin.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <note place="margin">I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h 3 36 <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Non dicit, ira Dei veniet ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per eum, ſed ira Dei manet ſuper cum, quamvis natu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>raliter damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti jam ſint re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probi ſua ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men infideli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate novam ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bi mortem ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerſunt.</note>2. That Chriſt being offered to them to deliver them from curſe and condemnation, and they wilfully rejecting him, they aggravate their ſins, and bring upon them the condemnation of the Goſpel; ſo that the Law and the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel both condemne them, the wrath of God, that formerly was upon them by the ſentence of the Law, abides upon them, and new wrath is kindled againſt them, becauſe they beleeve not in Chriſt the Son of God, and ſo comes the great condemnation oft mentioned, <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.19. And to ſet out the cauſe of mans miſerie, take it in this compariſon: A man lyes ſick of a feaver, he is told by the Phyſitian, unleſſe he bleed or purge, and take other Phyſick, he will dye; he is diſtempered, and will not be ruled, he dyes. The queſtion is, what this man dyed of? I anſwer: He dyed of a Feaver, that was originally the cauſe of his death. And then in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond place, he dyed of wilfulneſſe, becauſe he would not follow advice. In the great day of judgement men ſhall be condemned for their diſobedience; and next, which is the great aggravation of their ſin for infidelity, becauſe they beleeved not in Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>
               </label> Before we come to the next point, let us make a breefe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of this, and it ſhall be an Item to take heed of infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity, eſpecially of willfull infidelity, ſay not that ye will not come to Chriſt, neglect it not for he will take it ill, and that becauſe.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <note place="margin">Foure aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations of the ſin of infidelity</note>1. The laſt &amp; beſt words that ever God ſpake, were by Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt; and to contemne them were a greater ſin: he that deſpiſeth <hi>Moſes</hi> Law did ſin in a high degree, but what will betide him that deſpiſeth the glorious truthes of the Goſpel uttered by Chriſt, to honour him and the truthes he revealed, the ſweeteſt expreſſions were made that ever we heard of,<note place="margin">Luk. 2.14.</note> 
               <hi>Glory to be to God on high, Peace on earth, and good will towards men,</hi> the <hi>Jewes</hi> could not be ignorant of thoſe glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous manifeſtations, and might have bin convinced by them, we all do beleive the doctrin of the Goſpel, and we receive
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:114168:9"/> them, and are readie to come unto him, in the uſe of his Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances. But with our faith we muſt joyne all other graces, and the practiſe of al duties, we muſt do every thing anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the profeſſion of the Faith, or elſe we are in ſome meaſure guilty of the ſin of the <hi>Jewes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. There is no ſuch impediments to hinder us, as was to the <hi>Jewes,</hi> they might have ſaid, the Prieſts lips muſt preſerve knowledge, and the people muſt ſeeke the Law at their mouthes, and they ſay, that Chriſt is a deceiver, a <hi>Samari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan,</hi> and hath a Devill, theſe might ſtumble the <hi>Jewes,</hi> and keepe them from comming to Chriſt; but there is no ſuch let to us, the Goſpel is countenanced, Chriſt is received. In the Primitive times they were faine to ſell all, in Q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>een <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> daies, they went through the flames, or elſe they could not have Chriſt, theſe were great tryalls, they fall not upon us, and therefore our ſin is the greater, if we do not imbrace him.</p>
            <p n="3">3. We muſt give a reaſon why we did not come to Chriſt, why we did not beleive in him, why we did not accept of him when he was offered unto us, with all his Excellencies, he came to us, and brought with him righteouſneſſe, life, pardon, heaven and the glorie of it, and would have freely given us them, if we would willingly and freely have accept<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him for our Saviour; but thoſe that have rejected him, ſhall ſee with ſorrow the fruites of their infidelity, and cry out againſt themſelves for looſing ſo great joyes, and pulling ſo great torments upon themſelves, and as Malefactors in the day of their execution, lament their folly and obſtinacie, in that they would not be ruled, and that brought them to their miſerable end, ſo the unbeleever in the day of judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhall have it charged upon him, and he ſhall repeat theſe words in the dolour of his trembling heart, <hi>I</hi> dye and am condemned, eternally, becauſe I would not come to Chriſt, who would have given me life.</p>
            <p>Fourthly and laſtly, ſuch as refuſe to come to Chriſt, and to be guided by the doctrin of faith, may come to make an open defiance againſt him and his Goſpel, the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e is a great differancs between the wants of faith, and a con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rarietie to
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:114168:10"/> the faith,<note place="margin">Aug. in Ioh. 15 Magnum quoddam pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catum ſub ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerali nomine vult intelligi.</note> where this later is in the height of it, men come to diſſent from the truth, to deny it, and in time to defie it; and Chriſt the author of it; the beleever he honours Chriſt by acknowledging him by aſſenting to his truth, and caſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his confidence and affiance upon him: but the willfull unbeleever doth the contrarie, and offers much diſhonour to Chriſt by his deniall, his diſſent, his diffidence, and defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance.<note place="margin">Aqui. 2. 2 dae. q 10. Artic. 3. Infidelitas eſt maximum peccatum.</note> Therefore ſome (nay almoſt all) do judge infidelity to be a very great ſin, and others argue and indeaver to proove it to be the greateſt ſin of all.</p>
            <p>We come to the Second point formerly propounded, which is, That Jeſus Chriſt will freely give life eternall to them that come unto him.</p>
            <p>It is cleer that he underſtands eternall life, by his expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion elſewhere, <hi>I give unto them eternall life,</hi> and they ſhal never periſh:<note place="margin">Ioh. 10.28.</note> and ſuch as ſpeake to Chriſt about life, mention eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life, as the ruler that followed after Chriſt ſaid, <hi>Good Maſter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 18.18.</note> 
               <hi>What ſhall I do to inherit eternall life?</hi> ſo that the life which Chriſt offered, and the people ſought for, was eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life, and it was freely to be given them.</p>
            <p>Life is the beſt kind of being, and preſuppoſeth a cauſe of life remaining in and working upon a Subject capable of life, all things that are, yet live not; there is a being infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour to life, and thoſe that live, live not all a like, beaſts and plants live, yet not ſuch a life as man lives, for as the ſoule is, ſo is their life; beaſts have ſouls, and yet have but ſence, and ſomewhat like reaſon; men have underſtanding, and utter by ſpeech what they conceive, for they have a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable ſoule, and a more noble then beaſts, and if all differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence come from the act of the forme upon the matter, then the ſoule of man more noble will ſtill worke, (as we ſee it doth upon the body) to faſhion it into more excellent parts, and to make the houſe and roomes for it's own uſe, and therefore this life in man, comming from a more excellent principle, is above the life of beaſts. Among men ſome have the Spirit of Life in them, who were dead by nature in ſins,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 3.</note> they being quickned, have a more noble principle of life, and have in them the beginning of life eternall; ſuch as are
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:114168:10"/> alive to God, &amp; have union with Chriſt, they live in another kind then naturall men do; for in the ſpiritual life, the Spirit of God works on the ſoul, as the ſoul doth on the body, but firſt, the ſoule is a meere patient, which in the naturall life is the ſole agent, the ſoule is under the power of Gods Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and as far as Gods Spirit is above the ſpirit of man, ſo far is this life of grace above that of nature; therefore the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> magnifies this life in the regenerate, above the life of reaſon, not ſo much as mentioning it, <hi>In that I now live,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 2.20.</note> 
               <hi>I live by the faith of the Son of God, who loved me, and gave him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe for mee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Life is ſpread over the whole man, yet firſt and principal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly it is in the ſoule, and diffuſed through every faculty, and if we ſtand not too nicely upon the diſtinction of life, and the actions of life, we may ſay, that faculty lives when it is able to do the works that belong to it, as the minde lives when it knowes God, and is dead while it remaines igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant; the heart lives when it loves God, and repoſeth truſt in him; the affections live when they joy in God, and make fit expreſſions of that joy towards him; as we perceive the hand to live when it can ſtir and work, and when this life of grace continues beyond time, it becomes life eternall, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity to life in the world to come, is but as time in this world; <hi>This is life eternall to know thee: and he that beleeves hath everlaſting life.</hi> Faith in Chriſt, and knowledge of him,<note place="margin">Ioh. 17.3. Ioh. 3.36.</note> are made the beginings of life eternall, and becauſe it is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded as a reward in heaven, therefore life eternall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes the beginnings of the life of grace, and the perfection of it hereafter, it is the altering of our naturall lives, for all our infirmities and griefes ſhall be remooved, and for the ſpirituall life, all the graces that in heaven ſhall be of uſe, ſhall be perfected.</p>
            <p>Life eternall includes all things eſſentially neceſſary to make us happy, and alſo all additions and attendants to make it compleat: honour, and glorie, and immortality are in it, for ſuch as by continuance in well doing ſeeke for theſe, ſhall find them in eternall life. But becauſe the life of glory which Saints have in heaven,<note place="margin">Rom. 2.7.</note> is the ſtrongeſt motive
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:114168:11"/> that might have perſwaded them to come to Chriſt, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we muſt more fully explain that unto you, the life of glory will be in the whole man, but principally in the ſoule, and moſt in the cheifeſt faculties which are the underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and will, to the underſtanding refer the bleſſed viſion, to the will, the fruition of God, theſe two are the principall parts of the life of glory.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Vide Wende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lium qui ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit upple. Biel. diſtinct 49. concluſ. 4. qu. 2.</note>I am not ignorant that many writers make the viſion of God, in glory to comprehend all the happineſſe which the ſoule hath from him, but there is reaſon, and authority, ſufficiently to propound them diſtinctly.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In the life of glory, the mind ſhall ſee God, that is, ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and perfectly know him: for ſeeing is put for knowing, <hi>Now ye ſay, you ſee. Iohn.</hi> 9.41. <hi>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>w we ſee through a glaſſe dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but then face to face: now I know in part, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut then ſhall I know e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven as I am known.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.12. every one in heaven ſhall with their own mind underſtand all things, and know all perſons ſo fully, as may any way conduce to their happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and to the end it may be ſo, all weakneſſes, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfections of the mind ſhall be remooved, no ſimplicity, no ſhallowneſſe ſhall be upon any, Idiots and men of weake abilities, may have ſo much knowledge of Chriſt, as to bring them to heaven; but when they are there, they ſhall have ſharpneſſe of wit,<note place="margin">Prov: 1.4.</note> for full conformity with God in his Image,<note place="margin">Col. 3.10.</note> is a chiefe thing in life eternall, and knowledge is a principall part of Gods Image, as the Apoſtle plainly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ffirmes, <hi>Having put on the new man which after God is renewed in knowledge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The mind ſhall ſo cleerly underſtand as that it ſhall not need the help of faith, as it is now of uſe unto us, when we hear of the Trinity of perſons, of the union of the two na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures in Chriſt, of election, and of the reſurrection, we take them upon truſt, building by faith upon the truth of him that relates them in the Scripture; but in heaven we ſhal per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly know, &amp; underſtand all things which are now darke and obſcure, all controverſies ſhall be decided, all doubtes ſhall be removed, and ſurely our fight will be very cleer, when we ſhall not need the help and uſe of our better eye,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:114168:11"/> Now we walk by faith, and not by ſight; but then by ſight,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 5.7.</note> and not by faith.</p>
            <p n="4">4. To make us ſee the glorious things of heaven, there ſhall be no outward means, ſuch as have been of uſe on earth, no preaching of the Word, no Sacraments, no viſions, dreams or apparitions in bodily ſhapes; as ſometimes God hath made himſelf known to his ſervants in former times, to Patriarches, Prophets, and Apoſtles.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The means ſhall be the light of glory, which ſhines in heaven above all the brightneſſe that ever man did ſee;<note place="margin">Col. 1.12.</note> he <hi>hath made us meet to be partakers of the inheritance of the Saints in light.</hi> This light would dazle the eye of man, and dim it; for if the glorious body of the ſame would hurt the eye of a man, what would the light of heaven do? it being ſuch as none can approach unto. In this frail condition we cannot ſee God and live; when God or but an Angel appeared,<note place="margin">1 Tim. 6.16. Lumen gloriae corroborat, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellectum ad perfectam Dei viſionem elici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>endam.</note> how were men affrighted? and if that terror had remained, it would have overwhelmed them; but in heaven the ſpirits of men will be elevated, and inabled, to ſee with joy thoſe things that there will be manifeſted.</p>
            <p n="6">6. In that light of glorie, we ſhall not onely ſee the attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes of God, his mercie, juſtice, truth, and wiſdom,<note place="margin">Whether the light of glory be <hi>habituale lumen in in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellectu,</hi> ſee it diſputed at large by <hi>Greg. de Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent. To</hi> 1. <hi>part</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 227. Num. 24.17.</note> and (which we are apt now to queſtion) but the very ſimple pure eſſence of God (which yet we muſt not ſeparate from his attributes) we ſhall ſee and know God, ſo fully as our natures are capable of. In heaven there will be a clear viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on on our part, and a clear manifeſtation on Gods part; but both are from God, to make us able to ſee him, and to be willing to be ſeen of us: he will ſhew himſelf not darkly, and obſcurely as to the Church in former times, not terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly as on Mount Sinai, not a far off as to <hi>Balaam;</hi> not for a ſhort time, as in his transfiguration; but we ſhall dwell up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the contemplation of him; we ſhall have time enough to take a full view of him; yet this viſion is ſuch as we are ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of, our finite, ſcant ſouls, can never comprehend the infinite excellencies of the eternall God,<note place="margin">In heaven there is <hi>Viſio clara,</hi> but not <hi>comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiva.</hi>
               </note> but we ſhall ſee and underſtand ſo much as may any way conduce to our hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:114168:12"/>
            <p>But ſeeing we have begun with viſion, and it is taken from ſence, it may be demanded what our bodily eyes ſhall ſee in heaven?</p>
            <p n="1">
               <note place="margin">Matth. 17.2.</note>1. I anſwer. 1. The glorious manifeſtations of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of God in ſome ſuch ſort as was on the Mount, where we find mentioned a bright Cloud, his clothes were white as the light, and his face did ſhine. When God appeared in the Temple at <hi>Solomons</hi> prayer, the glory of the Lord filled the Houſe, that the Prieſts could not enter, and it was a vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible glory; ſome ſuch but far more excellent is in heaven.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The glorified bodies of the bleſſed Saints full of beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and brightneſſe, at the day of judgement we ſhall ſee a company of glorious creatures, thoſe on the left hand ſhall be an ugly company, and many of them deformed: for if we credit <hi>Durandus,</hi> and others, their ſins not being taken away, the fruits of ſin will remain upon them; the lame, the blinde, the maimed, Gods ſoul will more abhor them then <hi>Davids.</hi> But all comelineſſe and excellencie will appear in the Saints,<note place="margin">Mal. 3.17.</note> for they ſhall be as Jewels made up; a Jewel muſt be cut and poliſhed, it muſt have a luſtre ſet upon it that it may ſhine; and it muſt be ſet in gold: their ſouls and bodies are not yet ſo glorious as they ſhall be, now they are jewels, but they are rough and unpoliſhed, much corruption re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains, and thoſe graces they have are not ſet in gold.</p>
            <p n="3">3. We ſhall ſee the glorified body of our bleſſed Saviour, which will be a joyfull ſight; we ſhall ſee him that is dearer then all our friends; we ſhall ſee him that dyed for our ſins; we ſhall ſee him that was crowned with thorns, the ſide, and feet, and hands that were pierced, we ſhall ſee him not in humility and meanneſſe, but in the brightneſſe of his glory. And if the ſight of <hi>Joſeph</hi> was ſo welcome to <hi>Jacob,</hi> and that becauſe he thought he had been dead, and did ſee him alive and in honour alſo: the like and much more is here, we ſhall ſee Chriſt alive whom the Jews ſuppoſed to be dead; and in honour alſo, whom they imagined to be as they ſent him out of the world, a crucified Chriſt: but they ſhall ſee him whom they pierced to their ſorrow and ſhame: but we ſhall ſee him to our endleſſe comfort, for we ſhall ſee
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:114168:12"/> his gracious countenance looking towards his own with much joy in his face, and expreſſing it in ſome ſuch man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner as this: You have long looked for this day, you have mourned under many calamities, and moſt of all for your ſins; now the day expected is come, and now an end of all your ſorrows, all tears I wipe away; you have depended up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me for ſalvation, I am come to ſave you; you have recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved me, I am come to reward you, enter into your Maſters joy. And touching this ſight of Chriſt, it may be demanded whether it will be more pleaſant for us to ſee him, or for him to ſee all his elect together?</p>
            <p>For anſwer know, firſt who loves moſt, will moſt rejoyce. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Secondly, whoſe need is greateſt, that will cauſe more joy. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> In the former reſpect, Chriſt loves his own with an infinite love, and joyes in them more then they can in him: He who is the Bridegroom, in whom are all affections, it will be joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to him to ſee them altogether, for whom he willingly ſhed his deareſt blood. But in regard of our abſence from him, and the benefit of communion with him, we ſhall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly rejoyce to ſee him.</p>
            <p>But evill men, if in that black darkneſſe they can ſee any thing, it ſhall be to their terrour and vexation; for they ſhall ſee many wretched perſons like themſelves, from whom they can reap no comfort, and to whom they can yeeld no releaſe, they ſhall ſee a companie of perſons that when they come out of their graves, ſhall look with trembling coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenances like <hi>Cain,</hi> horrour ſhall appear in their faces, they ſhall be as ſo many priſoners that come out of the Goale to go to execution, and with gaſtly looks they ſhall behold Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt whom they have not honoured, whoſe Goſpel they have not beleeved, to whom they have not ſued nor ſought, but have vilified, and ſleighted the offer of grace made by him in the preaching of the Goſpel. But the Saints ſhall have all joy and comfort in that which they ſhall ſee, and not onely in fore-named particulars, but in all the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naments of heaven ariſing from the ſweetneſſe of the ſcitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of the place, and all thoſe excellencies which the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l cauſe to be there for the joy of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full.
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:114168:13"/> And if the skill of man can frame delightfull ſights which the world affects, &amp; runs after, as Masks and Shews, what kinde of ſights do you think will be in heaven? they ſhall be delightfull, and without vanity; they ſhall pleaſe in a ſolid and ſerious manner, and ſhall infinitely excell all the delights that ever your eyes have ſeen, or your ears have hard of: and that, 1. in reſpect of the partie ſeeing this glory who ſhall be made glorious, and every way both with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in and without: here on earth a poore deſpiſed man may ſee others in glory, and himſelf never the better for it. Our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour would not have prayed that thoſe which were given him might be where he is, and ſee his glory, but with a pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to make them happie in ſeeing it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. There is a perfection in regard of the generality, ſuch as far goes beyond the glory of this world: For in the Kings Court there are ſome that are poore, or deſpiſed, or diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented; ſome that are ſick, or in diſtreſſe, or in ſome ill caſe or other; and i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> either the King ſee a beggar, whom he is bound to pitie, or the beggar ſee the King, whom Nature may move to envie, here is no perfection. But in heaven we ſhall ſee all glorious, the King glorious, the Subjects glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous all of them, the place glorious, none to be pitied, none to be prayed for, none to be envied, nothing ſhall detract from your happineſſe; happie are thoſe eyes that ſhall ſee this glorious ſight, and happie thoſe ears that hear of it if you be moved to deſire it, and follow hard after it, and in compariſon of it to deſpiſe the glorie of the world. And let it be the care of all that hope to come to have this ſight, to take heed and not ſuffer their eyes to look after vanity, or to be eyes full of adultery; but rather let them be uſed in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding the works of God, and reading the Scriptures; and thoſe ſences that are taken up in any ſuch holy action, God will crown and honour.</p>
            <p>In the next place we come to that part of life eternall, which is in the will, and that is the injoyment or fruition of God, which is in ſome meaſure on earth, but fully and compleatly in the ſtate of glory; and though the fruition of God be in the whole man, yet we may refer it in ſpeciall
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:114168:13"/> manner to the will, for that deſires and longs after it, and the faculty that labours moſt ſhall be Crowned. Upon the more full knowledge of God in the cleer viſion, if any di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of time were between that and the injoyment of God, the heart would more earneſtly deſire it; and in a ſhort time be much perplexed for the want of it: the mind now doubts of many things, and is readie to diſpute the caſe whether God be mercifull, or juſt, whether there be a Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, then all will be cleered, and the ſoule will be taken with the excellency of God far above that which now it is.<note place="margin">1 Theſ. 4.15.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The fruition of God no man explaines it that I have met with, neither can it be expreſt, <hi>Paul</hi> tells us that the dead and alſo thoſe which are alive, ſhall meet the Lord at his ſecond coming, and ſhall be ever with him, as freinds that are together and ſee one another, and by ſpeaking commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate their thoughts do injoy one another;<note place="margin">Bonum eſt quo habito complete bene eſt hab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ali. Biel.</note> ſo and in a far higher way ſhall we injoy God, not in hope, nor in title, nor by faith, nor by his word and promiſe, but really, inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, immediatly, fully, compleatly, and this properly makes a man happie. And this proves God to be the chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt good, for in having him it will be compleatly well with the poſſeſſor, and the will of man will not quiet it ſelf, till it have God it will be reſtleſſe and unquiet, putting it ſelfe out in deſire; but in heaven it will be ſatisfied, and ſhall have as much as it can contain; and therfore ſhall deſire no more, becauſe it would be in vain, not being able to contain any more. If God will quiet himſelf in his love to the Church,<note place="margin">Zeph 3.17.</note> much more may ſhe quiet her ſelf in the fruition of God. But when we ſay the Will will be quiet, we muſt not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive any wearineſſe in it, or any lothing ſociety as in the things of this world; we on earth, like children, deſire that to day which anon we are weary of, tis not ſo here, we ſhall have no ceſſation of joy, which in worldly things is cauſed firſt, by weakning the active power of the Will; and it is a true Poſition, the will is not wearied unleſſe the active power be weakned and waſted. In this frail eſtate of nature,<note place="margin">Voluntas non fatigatur <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſi potentia activa d minuatur.</note> we ſpend our ſpirits in laughing, in rejoycing, in recreations, but in the enjoying of God, we ſhall have our ſpirits revived;
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:114168:14"/> and when we have been a long time in heaven, yet we ſhall have ſtill more joy: If thoſe that wait upon the Lord here on earth renew their ſtrength, then much more is it true in heaven,<note place="margin">Iſa. 40 31.</note> that thoſe that attend him there, ſhall have their joy and ſtrength renewed.</p>
            <p n="2">2. We are wearie of a thing when we come to eſpie any vanity in it, and therefore men have tyred out themſelves in ſeeking content in temporall things, and they all come to ſay with <hi>Solomon, All is vanity,</hi> there is an emptineſſe in the things, and vexation of ſpirit, namely to the ſpirit of him that looks for better; but in God no ſuch things, for the more we know him, the better we ſhall like him, and ſhall ſtill be enamored with him.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Beatus non eſt qui non fruitur quod amat. Deus plus di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligitur quam intelligitur.</note>In this world we cannot be fully happie, becauſe we have not what we love; It is a miſerie to a man, if he have not what he loves, or loves not what he hath; the ſoule lives in hope to injoy God, the will of man goes further in her art then any other faculty, ſence looks at the outſide of a thing, <hi>viz.</hi> colour; reaſon hath an idea or notion of it; but will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires the thing it ſelf: the heart of man is ſet upon God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf;<note place="margin">Charitas intrat ſcientia foris ſtat. Biel,</note> and as in heauen we ſhall know God more, ſo we ſhall love him more, and injoy him more, and none can tell what affections he ſhall have in heaven; the ſoule ſhall have a wide capacity and receive in much of God, which may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare by theſe two particulars.</p>
            <p n="1">1. God is ſweet in the uſe of his creatures, as meat to the hungrie, clothes to the naked, ſleepe to the wearie, fire to them that are cold, theſe are very welcome; but if God be taſted in them, they are ſweeter then ordinarie.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In the Ordinances, God is more to the beleeving heart, when the troubled conſcience can find reſt no where, if it hear of the mercy of God in Chriſt it is revived, the ſoule that groans under the burthen of ſin, if it be put in hope of pardon, it begins to look up, which before was quite down, and utterly dejected.</p>
            <p>But what need I to ſpeak how ſweet God is in his Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances? I appeale to all thoſe hearts that ever have received good by his word, whether it hath not been more then their
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:114168:14"/> appointed food, &amp; far above all the comforts of this world; but in heaven we ſhall injoy God, not in his creatures, nor in his Ordinances, but in himſelf; and we ſhall find the vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etie of all comforts to meet in him, we ſhall need no Sun to ſhine upon us, no wine to make our hearts glad, no oyl to make our faces ſhine, nay we ſhall need no Sacraments, no preaching of the word, but God in himſelf, and from him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, will communicate the fulneſſe of joy, and it ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue without interruption, without any mixture of ſorrow, or ſinfulneſſe; no devill ſhall be there to tempt, no deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe in our hearts to betray us, no worldly occaſion to entangle or trouble us; our hearts ſhall be lifted up and never fall again, our affections warm and never coole again, our mindes ſettled in the full aſſurance of Gods favour and never doubt again; our natures ſhall be perfectly holy and never ſin again, all our thoughts and deſires ſhall be ſet on God and nothing elſe; and for concluſion of this point, we ſhall be happie, and there will be no danger, no poſſibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of looſing it again: lo, thus ſhall it be done to the man whom God will honour.</p>
            <p>And now that I have explained what life eternall is, I come to the latter part which is to ſhew you that Chriſt will confer upon you this life by way of gift;<note place="margin">Rom. 6.23.</note> he will freely give it to you, <hi>The gift of God is eternall life through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord.</hi> And this aggravates the ſin of the <hi>Jewes</hi> that they might have ſo great a bleſſing in ſuch a free way of gift, and yet would not come unto him; and not onely the <hi>Jews,</hi> in the daies of Chriſt were to be blamed, but even in theſe daies the Papiſts will not come to him to have life in this way of gift, they will merit it, elſe they will not have it; they will not have a heaven that coſts them nothing. To meet with both theſe, I ſhall briefly ſhew you that Chriſt will freely give you life if you come to him, and that you muſt have it this way, or not at all.</p>
            <p>Chriſt purchaſed it, and meritoriouſly procured it, and it is freely given by him to us; he bought it, as if it had been freely given, &amp; it is freely given as if it had not been bought, it is Chriſts purchaſe, but our inheritance; Chriſt is given
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:114168:15"/> who bought it; the Word that works faith to apply it is given, the Spirit that inables us to beleeve, and to look after life eternall is given; And therefore the grace of God is made the cauſe of ſalvation in generall,<note place="margin">Ephe 2.8. Rom. 3.24. Ephe. 1.6, 7.</note> and alſo aſcribed to the particulars of juſtification, adoption, remiſſion of ſins, and glorification. And as God intended his glory ſhould ariſe out of the manifeſtation of his ſeverall attributes: ſo he purpoſed ſeverall works wherein they were to ſhine, and more eminently to appear; as his power in the Creation, the inviſible things of him,<note place="margin">Rom. 1.20.</note> that is, his eternall power and God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head are ſeen in the Creation; Wiſdom and Providence are chiefly ſeen in the government of the world; He made the Earth by his power, he eſtabliſhed the world by his wiſdom, and ſtretched out the Heavens by his diſcretion.<note place="margin">Ier 10.12.</note> Juſtice is ſeen in the condemnation of the wicked; and Gods free grace in the ſalvation of the elect. Yet we muſt not imagine that nothing elſe but power, and wiſdom, and juſtice, and grace, appear in theſe works, but theſe are more eminent and perſpicuous; and the Attributes of God though they be not ſubordinate or inferiour one to another, yet they give way one to another; as the Mayor and Aldermen in a Corporation, they give honour to him whoſe turn it is to have the chief place: ſo here, all give way to power in Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, none did ſo much appear as that; and all give way to Gods free grace in our ſalvation: and from thoſe words of the Apoſtle,<note place="margin">Eph. 1.6.</note> we were adopted <hi>to the praiſe of the glory of his grace.</hi> We may infer the like, he made the world for the praiſe of the glory of his power, he governs it for the praiſe of the glory of his wiſdom, he condemnes wicked men for the praiſe of the glory of his Juſtice; and ſaves his own for the praiſe of his glorious grace: And how dare any ſhew themſelves enemies to the grace of God? or go about to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure it, or derogate from the goodneſſe of Chriſt, who doth freely offer life to them that come unto him?</p>
            <p>That we may vindicate the grace of God againſt the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt and others, and ſhew that life eternall is not merited or deſerved by man; we will pick out an Argument or two, ſuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s ſee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to have moſt ſtrength in them, and anſwer
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:114168:15"/> them; yet ſo as to deliver the poſitive truth, rather then meddle much with the controverſie.</p>
            <p>There are two things alledged againſt this truth, one by ancient Writers, the other by Modern Papiſts; which ſeem to prove, that we are not to look for life at Chriſts hand of free gift. I will put them both together thus. If the holy actions, and ſervices of beleevers come from the Spirit of grace inabling them thereto, and ſhall be rewarded not of grace and favour, but of juſtice, then they are meritorious, and conſequently life eternall comes not by free gift, but is due to the Saints. But both the former are true, <hi>Ergo.</hi> The firſt is urged by <hi>Biell,</hi> and <hi>Greg. de Valentia,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Biel li 2. diſt. 29.</note> and moſt School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men that write of that ſubject. And they amplifie it thus: The nobleneſſe of the cauſe argues the nobility of the effect; the Spirit of God works in us, and by his grace we are what we are; our actions are not ours but Chriſts, which by his Spirit produceth them in us therefore.</p>
            <p>The ſecond, <hi>viz,</hi> that theſe actions ſhall be rewarded not of grace, but in juſtice, <hi>Bellarmine</hi> urgeth,<note place="margin">2 Tim. 4.8.</note> and quoteth the words of <hi>Paul; From henceforth is laid up for me a Crown of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, which the Lord the Righteous Judge ſhall give to me, and not onely to me, but to all that love his appearing;</hi> here he triumphs, for here is (ſaith he) juſtice or righteouſneſſe both in the Judge that gives the reward, and in the Crown that is given, and Juſtice gives every one their due, and if it be of due debt, it is merited. And he urgeth the like phraſe, <hi>If we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe our ſins, God is just to forgive them:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Ioh. 1.9. God would have wrought in <hi>Adam per generalem in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluentiam;</hi> he works in us <hi>per ſperialem inſpirationem quod munus noſtrum mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus merit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ium.</hi>
               </note> of all the arguments that I have met with, this ſeemes to be one of the ſtrongeſt.</p>
            <p>For anſwer to the firſt branch, it muſt be acknowledged that the actions of a man regenerate, are more noble then <hi>Adams</hi> could have been if he ſtood in his integritie; for his obedience had come from the liberty of his will, and from his own ſpirit: but now under the Covenant of grace, we have a more glorious ſpirit, the Spirit of Chriſt that works in us not by a generall influence; but a ſpeciall operation, quickning, inſpiring, acting and eliciting, every thing that is good in us. But though our actions are more noble, yet leſſe meritorious, becauſe they are leſſe ours then <hi>Adams</hi> would have been.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:114168:16"/>
            <p>For the ſecond branch, that God of juſtice, not of favour and mercie, is to give the reward. I anſwer: that juſtice is ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in ſayings or in deeds. The former is truth and fidelity which ſtands in keeping of promiſes, of which <hi>John</hi> ſpeaks, he hath promiſed pardon to them that make confeſſion of their ſins; and therefore if you do it, <hi>he is juſt and faithfull,</hi> (ſaith the text) one explains the other, and you ſhall be ſure to have the pardon of your ſins. Juſtice in actions is either legall, rigid, ſtrict juſtice: or elſe Evangelicall, tempered, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>layed juſtice, whereby God condeſcends as lowe as may be, parts with as much right as poſſibly he can, and ſo gives man a reward; which appears by the Apoſtles mentioning a <hi>throne of grace;</hi> a throne is a place of Juſtice, yet this throne in which God ſits is a throne of grace, erected upon the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of Chriſt, where ſtrict juſtice is moderated, and temper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,<note place="margin">Iob 9.15.</note> elſe it were a vain thing for <hi>Job</hi> to ſupplicate his Judge. We may have eternall life from this juſtice, and yet it is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther merited nor due.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> But if it will do them any good, we may ſay heaven is due,<note place="margin">Debetur per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonae non operi.</note> and yet hold it as a free gift coming from Gods boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie; It is due to the perſon by reaſon of his ſonſhip and ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption, not due to him in regard of any perfection in his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice and obedience to the heir. The inheritance is due (ſaith the Cardinal) we grant it, but how came he to be a ſon and heir? was it not free grace that made him ſo? yes doubtleſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> It is due in regard of Gods promiſe, for God hath made himſelf a debtor not by receiving any thing from us,<note place="margin">Debitorem ſe fecit Deus non accipiendo ſed promittendo.</note> but by his own free ingagement to us; and what moved him to make us ſuch a promiſe? It was his free grace and goodnes to us.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> It is due in regard of the Covenant of grace, whereby he hath made over Heaven to them that beleeve in his Son: If the condition be kept we are ſure to have it; But who in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ables us to beleeve? Is it not God? And what moved him to enter into Covenant? was it not his free grace? But now that the Covenant is eſtabliſhed, and Chriſt hath tendred a ranſome for us, and it is accepted; the juſtice and righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of God will not ſuffer him to require a ſecond ranſom,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:114168:16"/> or to deny that which is purchaſed for us. But let us leave this point, I ſuppoſe it is clear to them that deſire to ſee the truth.</p>
            <p>You hear there is eternall life which Chriſt will freely give you; and herein you have a view of his bountie:<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>
               </label> there are divers attributes in God which neither devil nor the worſt man can condemne, as love, mercie, patience, bounty, they have an amiableneſſe in them, and cannot be hated; and when Chriſt doth in his bounty offer life to men, he doth like himſelf; a man may give honour, wealth, counſell, but none can give life but God; and nothing can be accept<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, or indeed a gift, without life. If you would beſtow ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo much gold and ſilver, or makeover Land to one that lyes dead before you, nothing is done unleſſe you could give him life, and then they were fruits of your love and bounty; Chriſt will give you life, and leſt we ſhould undervalue this gift, becauſe life is accompanied with many cares, and griefs, and croſſes in the world, and if it were never ſo plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant, yet death comes and takes all away: therefore our Saviour offers eternall life, and this bountifull offer doth much aggravate the ſins of men that will not come unto him. But what ever Atheiſts and unbeleevers do, let thoſe that are wiſe and godly come to Chriſt, that their ſouls may live. And if you deſire this life, you will often enquire about your ſelves, as you uſe to do of the Phyſitian, when a childe or friend lyes ſick, Is he like to live? do you think he will recover? is there no danger of death?</p>
            <p>For direction, if you remember what was ſaid in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, life eternall is begun in this life, you muſt be made alive here, or elſe you cannot live eternally: and if you live by faith, and are quickned who were dead in ſins, I can aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure you, you ſhall live eternally: Bend then your thoughts to conſider whether you are alive or no, which will appear.</p>
            <p>Firſt, by a deſire to preſerve the life of grace: naturall life <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> is carefully preſerved; what phyſick, what bitter potions, are taken, what coſt are men at, what will they not do to prolong life? And ſhall men do nothing for their ſouls? will you live any where, not caring whether the Sun of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:114168:17"/> ſhine there or no? will you live in dark cellars or dungeons? or will you endure any unwholſome air? and ſuch are the places where the Goſpel is not preached.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Heat is a ſigne of life; cold is a fore-runner of death; warmth is a temper ariſing from divers graces, which we muſt carefully keep: <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.11. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the word ſignifies heat, and we would have our friends hot in our cauſe; we would not have a Counſellor that ſhould plead coldly, or indifferently, and ſhall we be indifferent in the ſervice of God? far be it from us.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Breathing is a ſigne of life; it befals many that are in ſwoonings and dangerous fits, that it is heard to tell whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they be: yet if they breath in wholſome aire, and pant after God, and the Scriptures, and after good advice to be ſet and kept in the way of Religion, it is an argument they live. I might follow the ſimilie of breathing in and out, but I ſurceaſe.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Thoſe that are alive, to chooſe would converſe with the living, and not with the dead; I would not have any one to think that I would inſinuate any ſuch matter, or ſuggeſt any ſuch thoughts into the heads of any that ſhould go about to tell who are dead, and who are alive: but we muſt not deny that which Scriptures plainly affirm, to chooſe a man that is not dead in ſins would not familiarly converſe with any but ſuch as he hopes in the judgement of charity to be alive; and it ſtands thus between the living and the dead, no fellowſhip, no commerce; if you ſpeak to a dead man, you are not anſwered; if you take him by the hand, and otherwayes expreſſe your ſelf, yet no correſpondence, no ſutableneſſe, your love is not anſwered again; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore there can be no joy in ſuch converſing. Speak to a worldly man, he can ſay little unles it be in worldly things, he is out of his element. And ſurely ſuch as rejoyce in good things, muſt needs cheerfully delight in the ſociety of ſuch as minde the like.</p>
            <p>And for further enlarging of this point, think what a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerie it would be for a man to marry a dead woman, to have her layed in his bed, carried to his board, to be with her
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:114168:17"/> continually, it would be irkſome and unpleaſing. You ſee <hi>Abraham</hi> would fain bury his wife <hi>Sarah</hi> out of his fight, for the face of death is irkſome and uncomfortable: And is it not the caſe of many a man that lives with a dead wife, and the wife with a dead husband? if it be no ſorrow to you, it is ſo much the worſe with you, for then you your ſelves are dead. A woman goes with grief, and is daily in ſorrow, if ſhe think her child is dead in her wombe, ſhe hath no joy to think of the time of her deliverance. O what is it to carry about with you a dead heart, a dead ſoul! And it is ſo if you be not moved in pitie to ſuch as converſe with you, of whoſe life in Religion you have no warrantable nor well grounded hope.</p>
            <p>But all you that by theſe or the like ſignes, can ſuppoſe and conclude to your ſelves, that you are now alive, I dare be bold to aſſure you that you ſhall ſtill live and live eternal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in heaven; many things may in this world trouble you, &amp; moleſt the comfort of your lives, but nothing ſhall cut it off, therefore with patience wait untill you injoy a better life then you now have, beare with patience ſicklineſſe of body, troubles of minde, the reproaches and croſſes of this life in hope of eternall life. And the conſideration hereof ſhould make us willing to undergo any difficulties, becauſe we hope to live happily, and that happineſſe to remain eternal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. And ſurely there is great reaſon why the ſervants of God ſhould wait patiently, and cheerfully expect the accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhment of their hope, for of all men in the world they are in the way to the greateſt preferment, and by faith they ſee already the bounty of God, which ſhal hereafter be manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed towards them.</p>
            <p>It may be of reproofe juſtly to tax and challenge the moſt part of Chriſtians, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe 2. </seg>
               </label> for not longing more after life eternall, what ſhould moove us to be in love with the world? Ah do we ſo much eſteem life that is temporall, it is a wonder to ſee ſo great matters mentioned in the Scriptures, and our hearts ſo little affected with them; and it may be a matter of wonderment, why our hearts make no more after things that be ſo pretious: I take it theſe cauſes may be rendered,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:114168:18"/> but all of them intimate matter of reproofe. Firſt men that are not aſſured of a better eſtate, are loath to leave that which they have in poſſeſſion, a poore man tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ives in a cold houſe and hath never a good roome, yet if he knowes not whither to go, he will not wil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lingly go out though it be never ſo cold; ſo is it with many men that are miſerable and poor, they have no aſſurance of a better eſtate and therefore they are loath to leave this.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> It may be they have ſome hopes and cares, and that honeſt and religious; as in <hi>David,</hi> he had a promiſe of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and his heart was ſet on the ſervice he meant to do, when he came to the Kingdome; this may be in the mind, and hinder the more earneſt deſires of heaven.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The maine cauſe is, life eternall, and the joyes of heaven are ſo high above our ſpirit, that till the ſoul be fitted by an extraordinarie meaſure of grace, and raiſed above an ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie pitch, it is not made ſutable to them: <hi>Paul</hi> that had viſions and revelations was elevated higher than ordinary; he was full of heavenly deſires.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Die Jovis 27 May. 1647.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>ORdered by the Lords in Parliament aſſembled, That Mr. <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentine</hi> one of the Aſſembly of Divines, is hereby thanked for his great pains taken in his Sermon Preached yeſterday before their Lordſhips in the Abbey Church <hi>Weſtminſter:</hi> And he is hereby de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired to cauſe the ſame to be Printed, and publiſhed; Which is to be done onely by Authority under his own Hand.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Jo: Browne Cler: Parl'.</signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>
                  <hi>I</hi> Appoint <hi>Joh: Rothwell</hi> to Print my Sermon.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Tho: Valentime.</signed>
               </closer>
            </postscript>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
